#大家好 現在弟弟們都胖啦
Hi everyone. Our younger brothers are now getting fat.
#是啊 我去山上砍點竹子
Really. I'm going up the hill to chop some bamboos,
#叫他們背回來
and make them carry the bamboos back.
#就在前面
It's right over there.
#去鍛鍊一下身體
I need to train them up.
#順便看一下有沒有野果之類的 找一下
We can also take a look if there are any wild fruits. We can check it out.
#我們往前面走
Let's move forward.
#你看 這個竹子都擋路啦
Look! This bamboo is blocking the way.
#把它砍碎
Chop it off!
#那尖的
It's sharp here,
#那麼尖
so sharp.
#哇 那竹節果
Wa! These are "zhujie guo" (untranslatable wild fruit)
#現在好多哦
There're so many of them now.
#青的 還沒熟
But they're still green, can't be eaten now.
#一樹都是
They're all over the tree.
#要到冬天打霜的時候才可以吃哦
We need to wait until it starts frosting in winter.
#好多哇
A lot!
#你看 這個榞果子長了好多哦
Look! So many "yuan guozi" (untranslatable wild fruit) have grown on this tree.
#這兩只螃蟹抱在一起不知道幹嘛 是不是在打架
I wonder why these two crabs are clinging to each other. Are they having a fight?
#哇 好多野豬來囉
Wa! A lot of boars have been here.
#都處都拱啦
They've dug everywhere.
#你看 這裡有一棵金綫蓮 (註︰終於寫對「棵」字了)
Look! There is a "jinxian lian" (chinese herb).
#就一棵
Just one.
#一棵 我們就不拔啦
We'll leave it here if just one.
#都被野豬拱掉啦
The boars should have taken the rest.
#這一大片都被野豬拱過啦
The whole area here is ruined by boars.
#怪不得沒有金綫蓮
No wonder I can't see any more "jinxian lian".
#你看
Look!
#這個酸棗
This is...sour date.
#野個都是被
These are all,
#野獸吃掉的 你看
eaten by beasts, look!
#它們直接咬的
They simply bite the dates.
#我們就會剝皮
We peel first.
#它們皮都不剝 直接咬
But they don't, just bite.
#把吃到裡面的肉 它就哇出來
They bite and eat and spit out the rest.
#肯定來了野豬
They must be boars,
#不是野豬就是
or some kind of,
#就是那個
sort of,
#反正是 它是國家保護動物來的
whatever protected species.
#你看 這邊 吃了好多
Look! Here. They've eaten a lot here.
#那邊 也吃了好多
There too.
#你看 那個酒飯團
Look! That is "jiu fan tuan" (untranslatable wild fruit).
#現在是青的哦
It's still green,
#還沒熟
not yet ready.
#等它熟的時候再來摘
We'll come again when it's ready.
#現在都長滿草啦
The grass is everywhere.
#你看 這顆[SIC]五子[SIC]毛挑 (註︰前面寫對後面又寫錯了)
Look! This hairy fig,
#好大呀
is pretty big.
#不次我挖回去燉
I'll come for it again to cook with,
#燉那個老母雞
with the old hen.
#這顆[SIC]太大啦
It's too big.
#等我家母雞呀
Let's wait until my hen,
#等我家那個母雞養 養肥一點
until my hen gets fatter,
#養老一點 我再來挖回去煲湯
and older, then I'll come again for the hairy fig.
#走了那麼久 終於發現一個
After hiking for a good whole day, finally,
#現個是熟的哦
this can be eaten.
#紅色的
It's red.
#你看
Look!
#哇 這個好大呀
Wa! This is really large.
#嗯
Um!
#味道不錯哦
It tastes not bad.
#像這種大的 又大又紅的這種
The large ones, large and red ones, like this one,
#這個很好吃
this one is very tasty.
#這種果子的味道
The taste of the fruit,
#有點這藤里面的味道 好多
is like the smell of the stem. It's full of,
#獨特的香味 (註︰其實這三行不太明白)
a unique aroma.
#好多拿藤果哦
A lot of wild melons.
#這青的 沒熟
But they're still green, and not yet ready.
#等熟的時候我們再來摘
We'll come again when they're ready.
#我們去砍點竹子回去啦
It's time to go back home with some bamboos.
#摘不到 現在還沒熟
Can't get anything. Not ready.
#好多果都沒熟
Many fruits are still green.
#砍兩根竹子回
Let me chop two bamboos.